<skills-catalog version="v4.0" dynamic-metadata="true">
<!--
================================================================================
Skills XML Structure - CLI + Dynamic Metadata Pattern
================================================================================
CORRECTED APPROACH based on user feedback:

1. KEEP load-skill CLI for discovery
2. Dynamically pull ALL metadata from skill files
3. Descriptions: 15-20 words (semantic richness, not minimal)
4. CLI commands execute against actual skill structure
5. User skills priority = 1, System skills priority = 2

TOKEN TARGET: ~2,500 (down from ~6,000)
================================================================================
-->

<!-- ============================================================================
SYSTEM SKILLS: Loaded with semantic-rich 15-20 word descriptions
============================================================================ -->
<system-skills location="00-system/skills/" priority="2">

  <category name="projects">
    <skill name="plan-project">
      Collaborative planning for new projects with deliverable endpoints. Uses mental models, creates 4-phase structure, pauses for review. Load when starting finite work.
    </skill>
    <skill name="execute-project">
      Execute existing projects by following steps.md task list. Tracks progress with checkboxes, updates resume state. Load when continuing active project work.
    </skill>
    <skill name="archive-project">
      Move completed projects to archived folder with metadata preservation. Cleans up active workspace while maintaining searchability.
    </skill>
  </category>

  <category name="learning">
    <skill name="setup-memory">
      Configure user goals, role, and preferences in 01-memory/goals.md. Interactive setup wizard with examples. Creates AI identity context for all sessions.
    </skill>
    <skill name="setup-workspace">
      Organize workspace folder structure in 04-workspace/. Creates workspace-map.md documenting custom folders. Validates structure and provides navigation guide.
    </skill>
    <skill name="learn-projects">
      8-minute tutorial on project workflows vs skills. Explains lifecycle, structure, when to use. Interactive with examples and decision framework.
    </skill>
    <skill name="learn-skills">
      Tutorial on skill system and creation patterns. Covers reusable workflows, SKILL.md format, triggers, and automation scripts.
    </skill>
    <skill name="learn-integrations">
      Guide to MCP servers and integration setup. Explains connector pattern, master skills, and external service workflows.
    </skill>
    <skill name="learn-nexus">
      Comprehensive Nexus architecture and design philosophy. Deep dive into execution engine, context system, and advanced patterns.
    </skill>
  </category>

  <category name="skill-dev">
    <skill name="create-skill">
      Create reusable workflow skills with SKILL.md template. Interactive prompts for name, description, triggers, scripts. Validates structure and creates folder hierarchy.
    </skill>
    <skill name="create-master-skill">
      Create master skill pattern for integrations. Shared library with authentication, error handling, and common operations. Template-driven setup.
    </skill>
    <skill name="import-skill">
      Download and install skills from Notion marketplace. Validates compatibility, resolves dependencies, configures for local environment.
    </skill>
    <skill name="search-skill-database">
      Search Notion skill marketplace by keyword, category, or tags. Browses descriptions and shows installation instructions.
    </skill>
    <skill name="share-skill">
      Upload skill to Notion marketplace with metadata. Validates SKILL.md format, sanitizes paths, publishes with versioning.
    </skill>
    <skill name="validate-skill-functionality">
      Post-execution validation of skill outputs. Checks files created, verifies expected results, provides quality score and improvement suggestions.
    </skill>
  </category>

  <category name="system">
    <skill name="close-session">
      Save session progress to reports, update docs, capture learnings. Generates session summary, updates core-learnings.md, marks completion state.
    </skill>
    <skill name="explain-nexus">
      Explain Nexus system overview and capabilities. Covers projects, skills, integrations, memory, hooks. Adapts depth to user knowledge level.
    </skill>
    <skill name="list-skills">
      List all skills with descriptions grouped by category. Shows system, integration, and user skills. Provides quick reference and search capability.
    </skill>
    <skill name="update-nexus">
      Update system files from upstream Git repository. Syncs orchestrator, skills, hooks. Preserves local customizations and user data.
    </skill>
    <skill name="update-workspace-map">
      Validate workspace-map.md accuracy against actual folder structure. Detects new folders, removed paths, missing descriptions. Updates map automatically or suggests changes.
    </skill>
    <skill name="validate-docs-implementation">
      Compare documentation against actual code implementation. Finds gaps, outdated instructions, missing features. Generates consistency report with fix suggestions.
    </skill>
    <skill name="validate-system">
      Validate system integrity with auto-repair capabilities. Checks file structure, YAML frontmatter, broken links, permissions. Fixes common issues automatically.
    </skill>
  </category>

  <category name="tools">
    <skill name="mental-models">
      59 thinking frameworks for decisions, planning, and analysis. Categories: cognitive, diagnostic, strategic, validation, etc. Interactive selection with guided application.
    </skill>
    <skill name="generate-philosophy-doc">
      Generate domain philosophy documents with standards and best practices. Templates for software, data, API, testing. Captures team conventions and patterns.
    </skill>
  </category>

</system-skills>

<!-- ============================================================================
INTEGRATION SKILLS: CLI discovery pattern with dynamic metadata
============================================================================ -->
<integration-skills location="03-skills/*-connect/" priority="2">

  <!--
  PATTERN for each integration:
  1. Connector skill (always present)
  2. Operations metadata (count, pattern)
  3. CLI command for discovery (load-skill {name} --help)
  4. Metadata dynamically pulled from skill files
  -->

  <category name="slack">
    <connector>
      <skill name="slack-connect">
        Initial Slack workspace connection setup. OAuth flow, token storage, workspace validation. Creates slack config and tests basic API access.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="12" pattern="slack-*">
      <!-- CLI loads this dynamically from skill files -->
      <cli>load-skill slack --help</cli>
      <!-- Metadata includes: send-message, list-channels, upload-file, channel-history, etc. -->
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="notion">
    <connector>
      <skill name="notion-connect">
        Connect to Notion databases by name. Discovery wizard, schema extraction, field mapping. Creates notion config with database IDs.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="8" pattern="notion-*">
      <cli>load-skill notion --help</cli>
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="notebooklm">
    <connector>
      <skill name="notebooklm-connect">
        Setup NotebookLM notebook and audio operations. Authentication, notebook creation, source management. Enables podcast generation workflows.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="10" pattern="notebooklm-*">
      <cli>load-skill notebooklm --help</cli>
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="langfuse">
    <connector>
      <skill name="langfuse-connect">
        Setup Langfuse tracing connection. Project configuration, API keys, environment setup. Validates connection and shows available operations.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="28" pattern="langfuse-*">
      <!-- CLI prevents auto-loading all 28 skills -->
      <cli>load-skill langfuse --help</cli>
      <!-- Returns: trace operations, observation ops, session ops, score ops, dataset ops -->
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="hubspot">
    <connector>
      <skill name="hubspot-connect">
        Setup HubSpot CRM connection. OAuth authentication, portal selection, property mapping. Creates hubspot config and validates API access.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="15" pattern="hubspot-*">
      <cli>load-skill hubspot --help</cli>
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="heyreach">
    <connector>
      <skill name="heyreach-connect">
        Setup HeyReach LinkedIn automation. API key configuration, account linking, campaign discovery. Enables lead management workflows.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="8" pattern="heyreach-*">
      <cli>load-skill heyreach --help</cli>
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="google">
    <connector>
      <skill name="google-connect">
        Setup Google Workspace services connection. OAuth flow, service selection (Gmail, Docs, Calendar, etc.). Creates google config with refresh tokens.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="7" pattern="google-*">
      <cli>load-skill google --help</cli>
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="beam">
    <connector>
      <skill name="beam-connect">
        Setup Beam AI workspace connection. Authentication, workspace discovery, agent access. Enables task orchestration and graph operations.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="10" pattern="beam-*">
      <cli>load-skill beam --help</cli>
    </operations>
  </category>

  <category name="airtable">
    <connector>
      <skill name="airtable-connect">
        Connect to Airtable bases by name. Base discovery, table schema extraction, field mapping. Creates airtable config with base/table IDs.
      </skill>
    </connector>
    <operations count="6" pattern="airtable-*">
      <cli>load-skill airtable --help</cli>
    </operations>
  </category>

</integration-skills>

<!-- ============================================================================
USER SKILLS: Auto-categorized by parent folder, PRIORITY 1
============================================================================ -->
<user-skills location="03-skills/" priority="1">

  <!-- Category detected from parent folder: 03-skills/slack/ -->
  <category name="slack">
    <skill name="slack-power">
      Advanced Slack workflows: extract channel schemas, prepare meeting agendas from thread analysis, digest channel summaries. Use when analyzing Slack conversations for patterns or action items.
    </skill>
  </category>

  <!-- Category detected from parent folder: 03-skills/research-pipeline/ -->
  <category name="research-pipeline">
    <skill name="paper-search">
      Search and download academic papers from arXiv, PubMed, Semantic Scholar. Query construction, relevance filtering, PDF download. Creates organized paper library with metadata.
    </skill>
    <skill name="paper-analyze">
      Orchestrate paper analysis with specialized subagents. Delegates to domain experts for extraction, synthesis, citation tracking. Manages multi-paper workflows.
    </skill>
    <skill name="paper-query">
      Query analyzed papers with progressive disclosure. Search by topic, method, findings. Returns relevant sections with context and citations.
    </skill>
    <skill name="paper-synthesize">
      Synthesize insights across multiple analyzed papers. Identifies common themes, contradictions, research gaps. Generates literature review sections.
    </skill>
    <skill name="pdf-preprocess">
      Convert PDFs to clean markdown with chunking. Handles multi-column layouts, equations, figures. Preserves structure while enabling text analysis.
    </skill>
  </category>

  <!-- Flat skills in root 03-skills/ → fallback "user" category -->
  <category name="user">
    <skill name="create-skill-algorithm">
      Create nested skill-chain workflows that execute multiple skills in sequence. Defines dependencies, data flow, error handling. Enables complex automation patterns.
    </skill>
  </category>

</user-skills>

<!--
================================================================================
CLI IMPLEMENTATION SPEC
================================================================================

load-skill {category} --help
→ Reads all SKILL.md files in 03-skills/{category}/
→ Extracts metadata from YAML frontmatter
→ Groups by operation type (if meta exists in skill)
→ Returns formatted list with descriptions

Example output:

Langfuse Operations (28 skills):

[Trace Operations]
- get-trace: Retrieve trace by ID with full tree
- list-traces: List all traces with filters
- create-trace: Create new trace with metadata

[Observation Operations]
- get-observation: Retrieve observation details
- list-observations: List observations with filters

[Session Operations]
...

To load a skill: load-skill langfuse get-trace

================================================================================
METADATA EXTRACTION
================================================================================

CRITICAL: ALL metadata must be dynamically pulled from skill files.

DON'T hardcode:
- Skill names
- Skill counts
- Skill descriptions
- Operation categories

DO scan and extract:
- Read all SKILL.md files in category folder
- Parse YAML frontmatter
- Extract: name, description, (optional) operation-type
- Build category structure dynamically

This ensures:
- Skills can be added/removed without updating XML
- Descriptions stay in sync with skill files
- No manual maintenance of skill lists

================================================================================
TOKEN SAVINGS CALCULATION
================================================================================

BEFORE (all skills with 50-word descriptions):
- 100 skills × 80 tokens = 8,000 tokens

AFTER (semantic-rich 15-20 word descriptions + CLI):
- 30 system skills × 30 tokens = 900
- 9 integration categories × 100 tokens = 900
- 10 user skill categories × 200 tokens = 2,000
- CLI overhead: None (executed on-demand)

TOTAL: ~2,800 tokens

SAVINGS: 5,200 tokens (65% reduction)

================================================================================
-->

</skills-catalog>
